Rafael Julio Lemos Silva

♥ São Paulo, Brazil • rafifos.dev **in** rafifos **?** rafifos

Summary

I'm detail-oriented and always strive to write clean, maintainable, and reusable code. I enjoy automating tasks and environments (Bash, Zsh, dotfiles, Docker, etc.).

Graduated in Systems Analysis and Development from Faculdade Impacta, I have experience with Ruby on Rails, JavaScript/TypeScript, and DevOps (containerizing services with Docker, CI/CD pipelines with Git-Lab CI/CD, GitHub Actions, and AWS CodeBuild), along with working with AWS, Kubernetes, Helm, and Terraform.

My main stack is JavaScript, TypeScript, Node.js, React, and Next.js.

I'm also active in Android OS communities, where I contribute with investigations, bug fixes, localization, and internal Android components.

Experience

Systems Development Specialist

São Paulo, Brazil Jul 2024 to present

International School Education

- Implementation of interactive student activities using H5P
- o Integrations with third-party services
- o Case studies on AI use cases

Senior Systems Developer

AeC

São Paulo, Brazil (Remote) Jul 2023 to Jun 2024

- Comment moderation for courses and articles
- o Public courses to expand the LMS's reach
- Bugfixes for SCORM contents
- o Optimizations for the LMS's performance
- o Reports for the LMS's usage
- Google Analytics integration

Senior Systems Developer (Remote)

São Paulo, Brazil Jan 2023 to Jun 2023

Stefanini Brazil

- Development of flows such as Power Outage Reporting and Facial/Document Recognition
- o Creation of the Digital Agency Homepage, focusing on intuitive navigation
- o Bug fixes and improvements to ensure a seamless user experience

Front-end Web Developer

Me Salva!

Porto Alegre, Brazil (Remote) Feb 2021 to Oct 2022

- o Participated in architectural discussions and the development of the company's Design System (MARS), collaborating with the design consultancy across all phases, from prototyping to implementation, ensuring standardization and visual consistency
- o Contributed to the rewrite of the Me Salva! platform using MARS, engaging in architecture, design, and feature implementation decisions, enhancing scalability and modernization
- o Developed internal libraries to improve Developer Experience, configuring TypeScript, linters (ESLint, Prettier), Jest, Conventional Commits, Rollup, semantic-release, and CI/CD (Heroku and GitHub Actions)
- o Developed an internal CMS allowing the content team to create and manage new pages, and content, improving the platform's agility and reducing the development team's workload
- o Acted as a technical reference for junior developers, providing support, pair programming, and assisting in the maintenance of legacy projects with improvements and new functionalities

Web Development Intern - Junior Web Developer Quero Educação

São Paulo, Brazil (Remote) Aug 2019 to Feb 2021

o Contributed to the development of new features, product improvements, and strategic innovations at

Quero, using agile methodologies and modern tools

- Developed critical features for the app (React Native), including Digital Enrollment and Branding updates, while also participating in React Native version upgrades to ensure best practices and performance optimization
- Enhanced the resilience and stability of the Digital Enrollment feature by fixing bugs and implementing improvements, delivering a smoother user experience
- Participated in a multidisciplinary team to test and validate new approaches to the company's business model, exploring strategic alternatives for expansion and innovation
- Contributed to the development of the Nota Quero application, part of the Vestibular Premiado project, focusing on performance and scalability improvements for both the back-end (Node.js with Nest.js) and front-end (React)
- Implemented horizontal autoscaling, adjusted Amazon RDS instances, and utilized Amazon SQS queues for messaging, reducing the application's response time from 10 seconds to 0.05 seconds, significantly enhancing the user experience
- Acted as a DevOps Associate, bridging the gap between the development squad and the DevOps team, implementing AWS solutions and Infrastructure as Code (IaC)

Systems Development Intern

Banco Fibra

São Paulo, Brazil Mar 2019 to Apr 2019

- Conversion of VB6 macros to SSRS 2012
- Creation and optimization of SQL queries
- o Support for the operations team with databases and reports
- o Development of solutions that improved the quality and speed of existing tools

Education

Faculdade Impacta

São Paulo, Brazil

BS in Systems Analysis and Development

Oct 2020 to Dec 2022

Universidade Anhembi Morumbi

São Paulo, Brazil

BS in Systems Analysis and Development

Jul 2019 to Sep 2020

FIAP

São Paulo, Brazil Jan 2018 to Dec 2018

BS in Computer Engineering

Jan 2018 to Dec 2018

 Health Tech Challenge: In partnership with the Beneficência Portuguesa Hospital, first-year Computer Engineering students were challenged to use new technologies to monitor and reduce noise in hospital corridors by building a line-following robot

ETEC - Escola Técnica Estadual de São Paulo

TVET in Informatics (Programming)

Francisco Morato, São Paulo, Brazil

Jan 2016 to Jun 2017

o For my thesis, along with a few classmates, I developed a game using the Unity engine, which was presented at the semester's project fair. The project was a low-poly FPS, and I used ray casting for the computation of gunshots.

Projects

Dotfiles

rafifos/dotfiles 🗹

- o Bootstraped my development environment with a script that installs all the necessary tools
- o Configured my development environment with Fish, fundle, and custom plugins
- o Management of multiple configurations for different machines
- o Private configurations signed with GPG for security

Iosevka Custom

rafifos/IosevkaCustom 🗹

- o Customized the Iosevka font with a few ligatures and symbols
- o Built the font with a custom name and variant
- o Created a pipeline to build the font with GitHub Actions, with the artifacts available for download
- o GitHub actions are cached to speed up the build process

atdownloader (Archived)

rafifos/atdownloader 🗹

o CLI tool to download anime episodes from Anime Twist

- o Written in TypeScript, using oclif
- Uses semantic-release to automate versioning, changelog generation and publishing to npm

com.riotgames.League_of_Legends (Archived)

rafifos/com.riotgames.League_of_Legends 🗹

- o Flatpak package for League of Legends
- o Used Winepak

leagueoflinux (Archived)

rafifos/leagueoflinux **∠**

o Snap package for League of Legends

rom_build (Archived)

rafifos/rom_build 🗹

- o Scripts to build ROMs and Kernels for Android devices
- o Optimized toolschains for ARM

flyme_device_motorola_ghost (Archived)

rafifos/flyme_device_motorola_ghost 🗹

- o Port of Flyme OS for the Moto X (2013)
- Kernel and device tree modifications
- o Customizations for the Moto X (2013)

Technologies

Languages: HTML, CSS, JavaScript, TypeScript, Shellscript (Bash, Zsh, Fish), Ruby, SQL, JSON, YAML, TOML

Technologies: React, Next.js, Node.js, Ruby on Rails, Docker, AWS, Git, GitHub, GitLab, Android OS, Android Studio, Android SDK, Android Emulator, Android Debug Bridge (ADB), Android Virtual Device Manager (AVD)